Maurice G. Fulton papers, 1829-1955
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Maurice G. Fulton papers, 1829-1955 (bulk 1870-1954)
MS 057
Fulton, Maurice G. (Maurice Garland), 1877-1955
Mainly comprised of historical materials on New Mexico, written or collected by Maurice Garland Fulton. Items include typescript drafts of books, correspondence, nineteenth century newspapers, newspaper articles, maps, audio-visual materials, diaries, poems, biographical sketches, legal documents, pamphlets, and photographs.
13 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Southwestern historian and English professor.
Organization
This collection is organized into nine series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1904-1955 (bulk 1926-1953)
Series II: Josiah Gregg, 1829-1941 (bulk 1842-1849)
Series III: Irwin Russell, 1875-1918
Series IV: Miscellaneous New Mexico History, 1842-1953
Series V: Lincoln County War, 1855-1954
Series VI: Billy the Kid, 1878-1954
Series VII: Clippings and Articles, 1829- 1954
Series VIII: Photographs, 1860s-1950s
Series IX: New Mexico's Own Chronicle, 1930s
Scope and Content Note
Mainly comprised of historical materials on New Mexico, written or collected by Maurice Garland Fulton. Items include typescript drafts of books, correspondence, nineteenth century newspapers, newspaper articles, maps, audio-visual materials, diaries, poems, biographical sketches, legal documents, pamphlets, and photographs. Some material is original, while some is photomechanically reproduced. Fulton's research documented the lives of men such as the Santa Fe trader Josiah Gregg; Southern poet Irwin Russell; cattle baron John S. Chisum, English entrepreneur John H. Tunstall, Governor Lew Wallace, and outlaw Billy the Kid. As part of his studies on the settlement of the Pecos River Valley, and also the Lincoln County War, Fulton compiled information on many of the local families. Photographs depict named and anonymous individuals; groups such as cowboys; gravestones; and different localities throughout New Mexico, particularly Lincoln and Roswell.
Includes annotated copy of Mary L. Moore's M.A. thesis inventory on the collection, which contains background information on Fulton, a bibliography, and detailed item descriptions.
Fulton, Maurice G. (Maurice Garland), 1877-1955 -- Archives; Russell, Irwin, 1853-1879; Gregg, Josiah, 1806-1850; Wallace, Lew, 1827-1905; Chisum, John Simpson, 1824-1884; Tunstall, John Henry, 1853-1878; Billy, the Kid; Pioneers -- New Mexico -- Photographs; American newspapers -- New Mexico -- History -- 19th century -- Specimens; Lincoln County War, 1878; Frontier and pioneer life -- New Mexico -- Lincoln County; Lincoln (N.M.); Roswell (N.M.); Fort Sumner (N.M.) -- Maps; Pecos River Valley (N.M. and Tex.); New Mexico -- History; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs; Manuscripts; Newspapers
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1904-1955 (bulk 1926-1953)
  - Correspondence, A-E. 1904-1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, F-K. 1904-1955 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, L-M. 1904-1955 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, N-Z. 1904-1955 (Box 4)
- Series II: Josiah Gregg, 1829-1941 (bulk 1842-1849)
  - Letters (photostats, typescripts). 1829-1941 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda (Independence, Mo.). 1846 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Articles written by Josiah Gregg. 1829-1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Articles written about Josiah Gregg. 1829-1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes, etc. 1829-1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Diary and Letters (drafts of parts). 1829-1941 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Diary and Letters (Indices, Table of Contents, footnote cards). 1829-1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Diary and Letters (Photostats of maps, illus., and photographs). 1829-1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Diary and Letters (v.1 final typescript draft). 1829-1941 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Diary and Letters (v.1 unbound printed copy). 1829-1941 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Diary and Letters (Reviews). 1829-1941 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series III: Irwin Russell, 1857-1918
  - Fulton: Mississippi Letters and Sketches. 1857-1918 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Fulton: Miscellaneous notes on Russell. 1857-1918 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Fulton: Fragments, Drafts, Notes. 1857-1918 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Fulton: Irwin Russell (completed draft). 1857-1918 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Irwin Russell: Correspondence. 1857-1918 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Irwin Russell: Poems and Articles. 1857-1918 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Irwin Russell: Materials from New Orleans Daily Times. August-December, 1879 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Irwin Russell: Articles about Irwin Russell. 1857-1918 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Irwin Russell: Miscellaneous material (clippings, etc.). 1857-1918 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Sketches A-Z, (Clippings, etc.). 1875-1918 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous New Mexico History, 1842-1953
  - Pecos Valley History (miscellaneous notes). 1842-1953 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Pecos Valley History (notes on articles in Roswell newspapers). 1878-1944 (Box 9, Folder 3-6)
  - Pecos Valley History (Newspaper articles, miscellaneous material). 1842-1953 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Chavez Company Historical and Archaeological Society. 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Old Timers Association (formerly Old Settlers Society). 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico Military Institute. 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Roswell Museum. 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Roswell (miscellaneous material). 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Kleinsmith: John Chisum Manuscript (various items). 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 6-9)
  - John Chisum (miscellaneous notes, etc.). 1842-1953 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series V: Lincoln County War, 1855-1954
  - Lincoln County History: Chronologies of Events. 1855-1954 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - John J. Cockrell: Correspondence. 1879-1890 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Ash Upton: Biographical and miscellaneous material. 1855-1954 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Ash Upton: Correspondence (to niece Florence Downs Muzzy). 1866-1887 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Ash Upton: Correspondence (to nephew Frank E. Downs). 1877-1889 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Ash Upton: Correspondence (miscellaneous). 1855-1954 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln County Correspondence (miscellaneous). 1855-1951 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
  - Miscellaneous Business Records. 1873-1900 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Old Lincoln County Memorial Commission and Lincoln County Museum. 1855-1954 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Lincoln County material. 1855-1954 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - War Department Court of Inquiry (Col. Dudley). 1878-1879 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Court Records. 1872-1890, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Documents. 1877-1889 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Real Estate Deeds. 1860-1889 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Records of various Federal Departments. 1875-1882 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Articles ( Mesilla Valley Independent). 1877-1879 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Articles (Typescript copies). 1870-1952 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Articles (Various papers). 1873-1884, 1928-1954 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Fulton's Notes (Manuscript). 1855-1954 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Fulton's Notes (Manuscript), Col. Dudley. 1855-1954 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Fulton's Notes (Typescript). 1855-1954 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
  - Material from Lew Wallace Collection, Indian Historical Society. 1855-1954 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Inventories of Letter and other materials loaned or given to Fulton. 1855-1954 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (John P. and John H. Tunstall) originals and copies. 1874-1878 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence (Tunstall Family, etc.). 1855-1954 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (John H. Tunstall to others). 1855-1954 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Diary (John H. Tunstall). 1875-1876 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Tunstall Estate: various documents. 1855-1954 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Tunstall material. 1855-1954 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Photographs. 1855-1954 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Billy the Kid, 1878-1954
  - Billy the Kid: Correspondence with Governor Lew Wallace. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Billy the Kid: Fulton Articles. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Billy the Kid: Magazine Articles. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Billy the Kid: Photographs. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Billy the Kid: Documents by and about Governor Wallace and Billy the Kid. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Billy the Kid: Miscellaneous material, including Fulton's notes. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Billy the Kid: Clippings. 1878-1954 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Clippings and Articles, 1829-1855
  - New Mexico - general. 1829-1855 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - The West. 1829-1855 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
  - Texas. 1829-1855 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - El Paso, Salt War. 1829-1855 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Mexico. 1829-1855 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Kendall, G.W.: The Texan-Santa Fe Expedition (photostats from the Daily Picayune). 1842-1843 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Local History Material. 1829-1855 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Series VIII: Photographs, 1860s -1950s
  - U.S. (exclusive of New Mexico). 1860s -1950s (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico: Places, A-Z. 1860s -1950s (Box 17, Folder 2-4)
  - New Mexico: White Oaks. 1860s -1950s (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Lincoln: General. 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Lincoln: County Court House. 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Lincoln: El Torreon. 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Roswell: General. 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 4-5)
  - Roswell: New Mexico Military Academy. 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - New Mexico: Gravestones. 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified (probably New Mexico). 1860s -1950s (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Cowboys and Range Activities. 1860s -1950s (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Places not identified (probably not New Mexico). 1860s -1950s (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Fulton, Maurice Garland. 1860s -1950s (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Persons: A-Z. 1860s -1950s (Box 19, Folder 4-5)
  - Group Pictures. 1860s -1950s (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Series IX: New Mexico's Own Chronicle, 1930s
  - Notes, Drafts, etc. on various chapters of the book. 1930s (Box 20, Folder 1-11)
  - Early typescript (with notes by ?). 1930s (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Revised Typescript. 1930s (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Another Version of Typescript. 1930s (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Various parts of manuscript including illustrations. 1930s (Box 22, Folder 1-8)
  - Newspapers and Photographs. 1930s (Box 23)